Guide to the Witchcraft collection, unbound manuscripts, 1560-1973.
Witchcraft collection, unbound manuscripts, 1560-1973.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Witchcraft collection, unbound manuscripts, 1560-1973.
4620
3.7 linear ft. (242 items)
Documents, broadsides, letters, and other manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Documents, broadsides, letters, and other manuscripts concerning witchcraft and witchcraft trials in Europe, mainly in Germany, through the early modern period, with a few documents from New England.
HISTORY OF THE COLLECTION
When, in the autumn of 1878, George Lincoln Burr -- still a sophomore at Cornell -- was entrusted by Cornell President White with the care of his historical library, the collection was allready well under way. White saw the witch-persecution as a particularly interesting form of fanaticism preceding the Enlightenment. He was a firm secularist, and, since his 1869 speech on “The Battle-Fields of Science,” the promoter of the so-called "conflict thesis" which postulated an intrinsic conflict between science and superstition, "scientific conclusions" and "theological control." In this never ending war of ideas, university libraries were viewed as arsenals. White used historical books and manuscripts in his history classes as early as 1872, and offered them to the curiosity of researchers. The period 1881-1895 proved the most fruitful for the expansion of the collection, with an increasing number of original and complete witch trial records (see for example, box 5, folders 1 and 8). When White was appointed as the first U.S. ambassador to a unified Germany (1897-1902), he found himself in a good position to buy from German booksellers. While witch hunts were seen all across early modern Europe, the epicenter of the phenomenon was Southwestern Germany and Thuringia. The peak years of witch hunts were from the 1560s to the 1670s, with more than 10,000 trials ending in executions. With family money and the proceeds from sales of his book "The History of the Warfare of Science with Theology in Christendom" (1896), A. D. White could afford outstanding documents, such as records of the witch-trial of Sister Maria Renata Sänger (or Singerin) von Mossau, charged with bewitching her fellow-nuns, whose execution was the last notorious witch burning in 1749 (box 5, folder 3). Her tragic case undermined the witch-hunt in Europe, and White commented upon it in chapter XVI of his book, "From Diabolism to Hysteria." He paid particular attention to the role played by jurists in fueling or denouncing the repression, for example in Rinteln, where Friedrich von Langenfeld wrote his "Cautio Criminalis" in 1631 (cf. box 4, folder 24), or in Ingolstadt, where the law faculty was particularly active (cf. 4620 Bd. Manuscript 35 ++).
In his effort to build a unique collection for Cornell Library, White could count on Burr, who once described himself jokingly as "a witch-hunter in the book shops." Burr had been captivated by the subject since he read an essay on the history of torture by Henry Charles Lea (1825-1909) at age fifteen. In 1885, while in Trier, he made a paleographic transcription of the trial of Dietrich Flade, ex-rector of the University and chief judge of the electoral court, who opposed the trials and especially the use of torture, and was arrested, tortured, strangled and burned for that reason in 1589 (Box 2, folder 8, and for the trial record, Bd. Manuscripts 4620 21++). Dietrich Flade, "the most eminent of the German victims of the persecution," became an icon to both White and Burr: he was a scholar who earned his fate through his attempt to check rationally and challenge the beliefs of his time. Having improved his paleographic skills in University of Leipzig and at the Ecole des chartes in Paris, Burr even started a doctoral dissertation on Dietrich Flade, and later published an article titled "The Fate of Dietrich Flade" (1891), conceived as a chapter of his never-written "History of Intolerance." In 1900, Burr initiated a correspondence with Joseph Hansen, the director of the Köln Stadtarchiv and a witchcraft historian who stood squarely within the positivist tradition. A Unitarian and a progressive thinker, Burr was convinced that witch hunting was not “the people’s fault,” and that clericalism -- more than "religion" -- bore the main responsibility for persecutions. Until his own death in 1938, he purchased original documents – though at a slower pace – and commissioned transcriptions of German manuscripts for the Cornell Library.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Documents, broadsides, letters, and other manuscripts concerning witchcraft and witchcraft trials in Europe, mainly in Germany, through the early modern period, with a few documents from New England. The unbound manuscripts and letters in the Witchcraft Collection include very interesting letters of George Lincoln Burr and Andrew Dickson White with dealers and with each other, concerning purchases for the collection. The George Lincoln Burr Papers #14-17-22 are another precious source for the history of the Witchcraft collection as a whole, and the purchase of witch trial records in particular.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bekker, Balthasar, 1634-1698.; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; Faust, d. ca. 1540.; Flade, Dietrich, 1534-1589.; Grandier, Urbain, 1590-1634.; Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.; Löher, Hermann, fl. 1676.; Loos, Cornelius, ca. 1546-1595.; Sänger, Maria Renata von Mossau, ca. 1680-1749.; Trithemius von Spanheim, Johannes 1462-1516.;; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Subjects:
Witchcraft--Germany.; Witchcraft--France.; Witchcraft--Europe.; Witchcraft--New England.; Witchcraft and sex.bib; Trials (Witchcraft)--Germany.; Trials (Witchcraft)--Europe.; Trials (Witchcraft)--United States.; Catholics--Theology.; Loudun (France)--Church history--17th century.; Puritans--United States.; Church and state--Catholic Church--History.; Church and state--History.; Women--Germany--History.; Women--Europe--History.; Women--United States--History.; Sex discrimination against women--Germany--History.; Sex discrimination against women--Europe--History.; Sex discrimination against women--United States--History.; Religion and law.; Inquisition.; Demoniac possession.; Magic.; Occult.; Torture.; Manuscripts--Collectors and collecting.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
George Lincoln Burr papers, #14-17-22
This guide covers only a small portion of the Witchcraft collection. There is also a large collection of books (ca. 3000 v.) held in the repository, ranging in date from 1487 onward.
CONTAINER LIST
- Manuscripts and Documents
  - A-B
    - Aa, Jacob van der, 1792-1857, circa 1850; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Manuscript copy of his article on Balthasar Bekker in his "Nieuw biographisch... van Nederlandsche dichters" document.
    - An den Teufel, n.d. (17c.); 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Manuscript copy of a poem.With manuscript annotation by G.L. Burr and partial transcription by LF
    - Anschütz, Anna, Defendant..., 1615; 48 leaves (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Fragments of trial records, containing accusations of witchcraft against a woman in [Zella-]Mehlis, Thuringia (Germany).
    - Arcanum Arcanorum, 1743; 9 leaves (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Manuscript copy of a Gnostic text.
    - Baer, Joseph and Co., Librarians and Antiquarians in Frankfurt am Main, 1899-1913; 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Letters to George L. Burr, Cornell University [Library], documenting the purchase of documents of witch trial records (concerning Sister Maria Renata Sänger or Singerin as well as Hans Loder's wife, 17th century).
    - Baer, Joseph and Co., Booksellers in Frankfurt am Main (Germany), 1907; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Typed letter to A.D. White [then U.S. Ambassador in Berlin] offering him witch trial records for purchase(Bamberg, 1617-31)
    - Basler Buch- und Antiquariatshandlung, Booksellers in Basel (Switzerland), February 1900; 1 leaf and 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Two manuscript letters to George L. Burr about the purchase of witch trial records (Alsace, 1607-75), one with envelope
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 1 leave + 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 8)
      List of works concerning Bekker, plus a manuscript copy of the poem "Aan aalems vreede schrijver ddomienee Zaalomon val til", signed "Baltasar Bekker" (?)
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Manuscript copy of the poem "Lof Geedight op den Roem der kristenen Geemaaakt door", signed "Baltasar Bekker" (?)
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Manuscript copy of "Bijschriften voorkomende in de gedichten uit het stamboek..."
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Manuscript copy of the poem "Lof Geedight op het euwig evangelium Gemmakt Door Joohannis Vlak prediekant tee Zutven", signed "Baltasar Bekker"; the signature was actually appended by the copyist.
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Manuscript copy of the poem "Lof Geedight over het verklaare van den eerste Brief van Petrus door Doomiene Golieus, prediekant tot hindeloopen" in Dutch, signed "Baltasar Bekker"; the signature was actually appended by the copyist
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Manuscript copy "UItrreksl uit het Kort bericht" [1692], signed "Baltasar Bekker"; the signature was actually appended by the copyist
    - Bekker, Baltasar, undated; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Manuscript copy poem "Brief aan zijn huisrouw, Frouk Fullenia" 1691), signed "Baltasar Bekker"; the signature was actually appended by the copyist
    - Braun, Marta, defendant, [1628]; 6 leaves (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Partial record of a witch trial against Marta Braun zu Mergentheim, 1628 [copy]. The original document is kept in the Hohenloe-Zentralarchiv (archive of the Hohenloe) in Neuenstein, Landesarchiv Baden-Württemberg (Germany), Bestand GA 55
    - "Processus Inquisitorius c[contra] Agnes Brussen, Michel Hoogens [Witwe] zum Grandshagen", 1679; 34 leaves (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Manuscript record of a witch trial which took place in Treptow (Pomerania). The widow was accused of having song hymns to the devil (trial "in cantationis"). The record includes the testimony of her neighbors, her own inquisition, letters from the local clergy, an order for torture from the Law Faculty of the University of Greifswald, her confession, and the sentence, according to which she was burnt.
    - "Acta Inquisitoria Catherinen Büchlers, die sogennante alte Bäckerin zu Grossmühlingen in puncto anno 1689", 1689; 128 leaves (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Complete manuscript record of a witch trial, Anhalt-Bernburg region, 1688-9, 240 p. in folio sewn into one fascicle. The former baker was accused of adoring the devil and having poisoned a neighbor (trial "in venesicii"). The record includes the testimony of her neighbors, her own inquisition, the fact that she was left to the torturer to be interrogated harshly ("to death if necessary"), two personal interventions from the Prince Carl Wilhelm von Anhalt, and the sentence, according to which she was eventually acquitted in the absence of evidence, and released after almost two years.
    - "Gela Hermann Büder Wittwe zu Rodenbach, Klägerin, Contra die Gemeindte deselbsten und sonderlich [contra] Johannes Krüdelbach und Johann Hansen [von dem] sleigen Ort, Bezüchtigung Zauberei belangend", 1650; 29 leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Trial record of a witch trial in Rodenbach, Hesse, Germany, 1650. The widow was accused of being a witch by two men of the same village. The document consists of her accusers' statements and her answers. Accompanied by a note by George L. Burr: "This manuscript was bought for the President White Library in the winter 1898-99"
    - Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938, 1886; 15 leaves (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Original text of a lecture titled "On the Loos Manuscripts," on witch hunting and the persecution for heresy in Europe ("that strange nightmare that fell upon the world just as it woke from the long sleep of the Middle Ages") delivered by Burr on October 6, 1886, at a meeting of the Historical and Political Science Association; with a full transcription.
  - C-F
    - "Dietrich Flade" [a famous witchcraft trial of the 16th century], 1883; Included are Prof. Carpenter's article from "The Library of Cornell University," no.5 of April 1883, as well as notes. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Discours sur la mort et condemnation de Charles de Franchillon, Baron de Chenevières, exécuté en Place de Grève pour crime de sortilège et de magie le 14 May 1626", [19th century]; 10 leaves (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Manuscript copy of a document kept in the Bibliotheque Nationale, Impr. Ln2 4768
    - "Criminal Prozess" against Catarina Drencken, held in Neuerburg, Luxembourg, 1613; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Fragment of a withcraft trial record: preliminary statement by the prosecutor and testimony of one witness.
    - Ewen, Baron Cecil L'Estrange, 1877-1949, 1933-1935; 2 leaves and 2 leaves and 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Three letters to George Burr by Ewen, the author of "Witch Hunting and Witch Trials: The Indictments for Witchcraft From the Records of 1373 Assizes Held for the Home Circuit A. D. 1559-1736," 1929.
    - Extract Pfarr Protocols, Tennenberg, Germany, 1653; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Statement by several "witnesses" that a woman named Stolz "turns herself into a wolf, and very often into a bear too"
    - "Grandier est mort", August 23, 1634 [?]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Autograph letter signed "F," sent from Poitiers. Describes the last days of Urbain Grandier, who was publicly burned in Loudun on August 18, 1634, after being convicted of witchcraft, specifically for his involvement in the Loudun Possessions. The letter reports certain "symptoms" of Grandier's alleged adoration of the Devil.
    - "Inquisition. Acta Contra Hans Fiedler, und Margaretha dessen Eheweib, zu Schönau, wegen verdächtiger Hexerei", 1663; 122 leaves (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Manuscript containing the preliminary statement, the testimony of seventeen "witnesses," as well as the trial proper of Hans and his wife, who was tortured to death in Schleusingen, Thuringia.
    - "Transcript of the Trial for Witchcraft of Dr. Dietrich Flade of Trier, 1589", [1589]; 67 leaves (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Paleographic transcription made by Burr in 1882 of the minutes of a trial record (Trier Stadtbibliothek Hs. 1533a/171). The Witch trials of Trier (Germany) in the years from 1581 to 1593 led to the death of about three hundred and seventy people, including Judge Dietrich Flade, ex-rector of the university and dean of its law school, who opposed the persecutions and especially the use of torture. He was accused of participation in a sabbat where he had arrived in a silver carriage drawn by four dark horses. The document is mentioned in President White's 1896 book(A History of the Warfare of Science With Theology..., I, p. 357, Rare BL 245 .W58 1896).
    - "Fragen... Contra Elsa Misseler", circa 1630; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Summary of a trial record [Hexenprozess in Flamersheim, Germany]
    - Furman, Gabriel, 1800-1854, 1825; 64 pages (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Contains the manuscript of an essay, "American Legends, Ghost Stories, and Witchcraft" written by Judge Furman of Brooklyn in 1825.
    - Furman, Gabriel, 1800-1854, undated [circa 1820]; "American Superstitions" (Box 2, Folder 11)
      17 sets of notes.
  - G-K
    - [Litigation concerning the payment of court costs in Tennenberg], 1654-1665; 18 leaves (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Concerns Hanswolf Gasserstedt's payment of court costs for his wife, Judith Rommelmann, who had been banished for witchcraft.
    - Gause, Anna, defendant, 1689; 18 leaves (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Partial transcript and notes on the manuscript of a trial. Defendant was Anna Gause, the 70-year-old widow of Klaus Zauman, accused of being a witch and strangled.
      Complete record, call number: 4620 Bd. Manuscript. 25 ++
    - Der Geistliche Doktor Faust: Eine Citation, n.d.; 8 leaves (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Partial transcript of esoteric notes.
    - Godard, George Seymour, 1865-1936 [State Librarian of Connecticut], 1914; Typed list, with the letter of transmittal signed by Godard. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      List of material on witchcraft in the Connecticut State Library (31 articles)
    - Good, William, September 13, 1710 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Autograph letter signed to the Honourable Commitee. Document concerning "the destruction of [his] poor family" since Good's wife, Sarah, was executed in Salem in July 1692 "upon the account of supposed witchcraft"; also mentioned are "a sucking child [who] died in prison before the mother's execution" and another "child of four of five years old [who] was in prison seven or eight months and being chained in the dungeon was so hardly terrified that she [now] has no reason to govern herself." Included are two letters from the secretary of the Essex Intitute, 1913, as well as an auction catalog, in which the letter is described, sale item # 805.
    - [Greiess, Eva, defendant]: "Zwischen Domminus Wilhlem Kurfürstlich Herrschaft Neuerburg... und Feminus Eva", 1629; 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Autograph document signed. Advice of the Luxembourg authorities, in the name of the Grand-Duke, reporting the torture, confession, and execution by "strangulation by naked hands" of an alleged witch. With partial transcription and translation.
    - Hall, Ralph, defendant, [1665]; 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Autograph document [copy by Judge Gabriel Furman]. One of the two copies of the bill of indictement for the trial of Ralph Hall and his wife, annotated by Furman, according to whom this was "the only trial for that offence in [the state of New York]."
    - Halle Antiquariat, 1906; 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Autograph letter signed from a German bookseller to Burr. Offers him "Protokolle von Hexenprocessen zu Flammersheim...aus den Jahren 1629-30" for purchase.
    - Happe, Hans, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Partial transcription and bibliographic description of Happe's treaty on alchemy, call number: 4620 Bd. Manuscript 77
    - Harrisson, Katherine, of Hartford,Connecticut, [1669]; 7 leaves (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Copy of trial records made by Burr, with his annotations.
    - Hencke, Barbara, defendant [Luxembourg], 1621; 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Judicial order for the torture of "Barbara, Beclagtin und Behaeftin," on the charge of witchcraft.
    - Henot, Katharina, [1627]; 18 leaves (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Photostat copies of records of a famous witchcraft trial that took place in Cologne, with a letter from Dr. Hansen, Historisches Archiv, Köln, to Burr.
    - [Hexenprozess, Luxembourg], 1621 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Fragment of a trial record
    - "Criminal Acta über Agnes Hinterreger und seiner Kinder [Christian, Thomas, und Einhard] in Crimine Maior de Anno 1687", 1686-7; 50 leaves (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Incomplete record of a witchcraft trial held in Carinthia, Austria
    - James I, King of England, [1591]; 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Tolbooth speech as to witchcraft [copy]. Copy made by Lucy Dreicker in 1929. Attached is a letter requesting payment from Burr.
    - Keiner, Osanna, defendant, 1662; 18 leaves (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Two documents relating to her trail for witchcraft: one describing the "great tumult" which took place in her cell and was supposedly caused by supernatural beings, and the other attributing her death under torture to strangulation by the devil.
    - Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683, [1635?]; 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      "The Copye of a Letter Written by Mr. Thomas Killigrew." Contemporary manuscript copy of a well-known account of the possession of the nuns of Loudun, composed as a letter by the future dramatist Thomas Killigrew, then aged 23, during his tour of France.
      Other manuscript copies are Bodleian Library, Ashmole manuscript 800, art. iii, ff. 21-27r, Magdalene College, Cambridge, Pepys Library 2099(3), ff. 10r-25v, and the British Library, Add. manuscript 27402, ff. 69r-71v. Source:
      J. Lough and D.E.L. Crane, "Thomas Killigrew and the possessed nuns of Loudon: the text of a letter of 1635," Durham University Journal, v.78, no.2, 1986, p. 259-68.
    - "De Klinkende bel", undated; 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Copy of a Dutch poem composed in 1662.
    - Knooulton or Knowlton, Thomas, and others: Deposition against Rachel Clinton for Practice of Witchcraft, 1687?; 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      One of the few remaining accounts of a witch hunt before the trials of 1692-1693. From the Phillips Collection (Harbin Papers), with a full transcription. "It demonstrates that neighborood suspicion of Rachel Clinton long antedated her trial in connection with the Salem outbreak" (John Putnam Demos, Entertaining Satan, 1983, p. 20. The author observes that the heading on this document, "Witchcraft 1687," is in a separate hand and was probably added at some later time.)
    - Kort-bondige... beschryving van Moses, in het boek der Scheppinge, 1699; 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Manuscript review of an article, by Johannes Roman, Boekverkooper.
    - Krämer, Margaretha, defendant, 1662; 55 ll. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      [Trial for Witchcraft in Suhl, Germany]. Various documents relating to the trial of a widow accused of being a witch ("der Hexerey wegen"), who confessed before being tortured, was sentenced to death by fire -- sentenced commuted to death by decapitation by the Duke Moritz von Sachsen-Zeitz, Administrator des Stifts Naumburg, after she showed repentance (rescriptum.)
      Complementary source: Bundesarchiv Koblenz, FSg.2/1-F Film Nr. 39 Suhl.
    - K[rist?], Bekker's portrait], 1838?; 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Copy of a short notice issued in the "Nederlansch Archief"
    - Kühn, Sebastian, 1662; 1 l. (Box 3, Folder 23)
      "Dass den vier Herrn Geistlichen und dem Kirchner zu Schleusingen der Herr Ambtschreiber Sebastian Bentzinger 2 fl[orins] 5 g[ulden] 3 d[ucats] von Irmel Wagnerin zu Breitenbach... entrichtet und bezahlt [die ich richtig bekommen habe]." Sebastian Kühn certifies to the payment to himself, as well as to four other clergymen or sacristans, of a sum taken from the estate of Irmel Wagnerin, who had been executed for witchcraft after examination by those "skilled theologicians [periti]".
  - L-P
    - "[Prozess] gegen die Witwe Lamkers, Maria, zu Neuerburg [Luxemburg], Lasters Zauberey halber", circa 1630; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Deposition against Maria Lamkers made by the city attorney "ex officio."
    - Laubardemont, Jean de, 1590-1653, to Cardinal de Richelieu, 1635; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Account by Laubardemont [a Capuchin monk and Richelieu's agent] of the successful exorcism of the Ursuline Prioress of Loudun, one year after the execution of Urbain Grandier. A fifth demon has been expelled from the body of the nun, leaving the name "Joseph" on her left hand.
    - Lea, Henry Charles, 1825-1909, undaetd [circa 1880]; 79 leaves (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Transcriptions of clippings collected by Lea, which he lent to Burr for copying (1889). Includes "Russian Witches," "Strange French Stories," "Superstition in Western Kentucky," "Pennsylvania Witchcraft: A Curious Case in Dauphin County," "Mojave Indians Sacrifice a Squaw accused of Witchcraft," etc. Burr worked to complete the manuscript of Lea's "Materials for a Study of Witchcraft."
    - Leitschuh, Dr. Friedrich, to Joseph Baer and Co., forwarded to George L. Burr, 1899; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 4)